Guide to the Engelbert Schucking Papers MC.255
New York University Archives
Engelbert Schucking Papers
1973-2015
New York University Archives
Schucking, E. L. (Engelbert L.)
Schucking, Heffa
Surowitz, Eugene J.
MC.255
2.25 linear feet in 2 record cartons and 1 legal half manuscript box
45 Reels
Engelbert Schücking (1926-2015) was a physics professor at New York University whose research interests included theoretical astrophysics, general relativity, and cosmology. Schücking was born in Hörde, Germany and studied mathematics and physics at the University of Münster, and later at Göttingen. He worked with German physicist Pascual Jordan in Hamburg in 1952, and earned his PhD there in 1955.He moved to the United States in 1961, and held research and teaching positions at Syracuse University, Cornell University, and the University of Texas at Austin. In 1967, he was appointed as Professor of Physics at New York University. This collection consists of audio reel recordings of Engelbert Schucking as part of New York University's Sunrise Semester, and a copy of the 2015 book Einstein's Apple by Engelbert Schücking and Eugene J. Surowitz.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of audio reel recordings of Engelbert Schücking as part of New York University's Sunrise Semester, and a copy of the 2015 book Einstein's Apple by Engelbert Schücking and Eugene J. Surowitz. This volume was published after Schücking's death and represents the final published collaboration between Surowitz and Schücking.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection donated by Heffa Schücking in March 2016; the accession number associated with this gift is 2016.030. An accretion of material was donated by Eugene Surowitz in 2016. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.035.
Biographical Note
Engelbert Schücking (1926-2015) was a physics professor at New York University whose research interests included theoretical astrophysics, general relativity, and cosmology. Schücking was born in Hörde, Germany and studied mathematics and physics at the University of Münster, and later at Göttingen. He worked with German physicist Pascual Jordan in Hamburg in 1952, and earned his PhD there in 1955. He moved to the United States in 1961, and held research and teaching positions at Syracuse University, Cornell University, and the University of Texas at Austin. In 1967, he was appointed as Professor of Physics at New York University.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Astrology.; Astronomy.; Educational television programs; Physics -- Study and teaching -- United States; Schucking, Heffa; Surowitz, Eugene J.
- Series I: Audio reels
  Housing Annotations:
  Box 2 contains empty 1/4" open reel audio box (labeled as box 18) with note reading, "Tapes 1-45 43 tapes - 23 double, 1 "not recorded" missing 18 22 43 2 tapes without numbers box 18"
  - Astro #1, 1973-01-18; 1973-01-29; cuid284 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 34)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Original Format: 1/4" Open Reel Audio, Duration: 30 min, Preservation Note: "Full track, mono; 7.5 ips; uni-directional; stored tails out"
  - Astro #2, 1973-01-18; 1973-01-31; cuid285 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 35)
    Original Format: 1/4" Open Reel Audio, 31 min., Preservation Note: "Full track, mono; 7.5 ips; uni-directional; stored tails out."
  - Astro Ep 3 - 73, 1973-01-25; 1973-02-02; cuid286 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 36)
    Original Format: 1/4" Open Reel Audio, Duration: 31 min., Preservation Note: "Full track, mono; 7.5 ips; uni-directional; stored tails out."
  - Astro Ep 4, 1973-01-25; 1973-02-05; cuid287 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 37)
  - Astro 5, 1973-01-25; 1973-02-07; cuid288 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 38)
    Original Format: 1/4" Open Reel Audio, Duration: 31 min, Preservation Note: Full track, mono; 7.5 ips; uni-directional; stored tails out"
  - Sunrise Semester Astrology #6 - Dr. Engelbert Schucking, 1973; cuid289 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 39)
    Original Format: 1/4" Open Reel Audio, Duration: 31 min., Preservation Note: "Full track, mono; 7.5 ips; uni-directional; stored tails out"
  - Sunrise Semester Astrology #7, 1973; cuid290 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 40)
  - Sun Sem. Astrology #8, 1973; cuid291 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 41)
    Original Format: 1/4" Open Reel Audio, Duration: 31 min., Preservation Note: "Full track, mono; 7.5 ips; uni-directional"
  - Semester - #9 - Astro #9, 1973-02-08; 1973-02-16; cuid292 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 42)
  - Semester #10 AST-10, 1973-02-08; 1973-02-19; cuid293 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 43)
    Container reads "Transcribed 10/10/75"
  - Semester #11, 1973-02-08; 1973-02-21; cuid294 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 44)
  - Sunrise Semester Astro #12, 1973-02-15; 1973-02-23; cuid295 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 45)
  - Sunrise Semester Astro #13, 1973-02-15; 1973-02-26; cuid296 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 46)
    Original Format: 1/4" Open Reel Audio, Duration: 31 min., Preservation Note: "Full track, mono; 7.5 ips; uni-directional; stored tails out; Sporadic static bursts throughout; 00:10:30;xx-00:11:00;xx - O-blank content [microphone was probably being adjusted as the sporadic static bursts stop at this point]"
  - Sunrise Semester Astro #14, 1973-02-15; 1973-02-28; cuid297 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 47)
    Original Format: ¼" Open Reel Audio, Duration: 31 min., Preservation Note: "Full track, mono; 7.5 ips; uni-directional; stored tails out"
  - Sunrise Semester Astro #15, 1973-02-22; 1973-03-02; cuid298 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 48)
    Original Format: 1/4" Open Reel Audio, Duration: 30 min., Preservation Note: "Full track, mono; 7.5 ips; uni-directional; stored tails out"
  - Sunrise Semester Astro #16, 1973-02-22; 1973-03-05; cuid299 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 49)
  - Sunrise Semester Astro #17, 1973-02-22; 1973-03-07; cuid300 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 50)
  - Sunrise Semester Astrology #18, Part 1, cuid328 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255)
    Original Format: 1/4" Open Reel Audio, Duration: 21 min., Preservation Note: "Full track, mono; 7.5 ips; uni-directional; stored tails out"
  - Sunrise Semester Astrology #18, Part 2, cuid327 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255)
    Original Format: 1/4" Open Reel Audio, Duration: 10 min., Preservation Note: "Part 2 of Lecture #18 from the Schucking series; Full track, mono; 7.5 ips; uni-directional"
  - Astro 19, 1973-03-01; 1973-03-12; cuid301 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 117, Item 51)
  - Astro #20, 1973-03-01; 1973-03-20; cuid302 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 1)
  - Sun. Sem. Astro #21, 1973-03-08; cuid303 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 2)
  - Sun. Sem. Astro #22, 1973-03-08; cuid304 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 3)
  - Sun. Sem. Astro #23, 1973-03-08; 1973-03-21; cuid305 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 4)
    "Not yet recorded" written in pencil under title, however the content contains episode #23.
  - Astro #24, 1973-03-15; 1973-03-23; cuid306 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 5)
  - Astro #25, 1973-03-15; 1973-03-21; cuid307 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 6)
  - Astro #26, 1973-03-15; 1973-03-28; cuid308 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 7)
  - Sun. Sem. Astro #27, 1973-03-21; 1973-03-30; cuid309 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 8)
    Box reads "Transcribed 11/30/75"
  - Sunrise Semester Astro #28, 1973-03-21; 1973-04-08; cuid310 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 9)
  - Sun. Sem. Astro #29, 1973-03-21; cuid311 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 10)
  - Sunrise Semester Episode Astro #30, 1973-03-22; 1973-04-06; cuid312 (Box 1, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 11)
  - Sunrise Semester Astro Episode #31, 1973-03-22; 1973-04-09; cuid313 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 12)
    Original Format: 1/4" Open Reel Audio, Duration: 31 min., Preservation Note:"Full track, mono; 7.5 ips; uni-directional; stored tails out"
  - Sunrise Semester Episode Astro #32, 1973-03-22; 1973-04-11; cuid314 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 13)
  - Astro--Sunrise Episode #33, 1973; cuid315 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 14)
    Original Format: 1/4" Open Reel Audio, Duration 33 min., Preservation Note: "Full track, mono; 7.5 ips; uni-directional; stored tails out"
  - Sunrise Semester Astro #34, 1973; cuid316 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 15)
    Box reads, "Transcribed 12/5/75"
  - Sun. Sem. Astro #35, 1973; cuid317 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 16)
    Box reads, "Transcribed 12/1/75"
  - Sunrise Semester - (Astro #36), 1973-04-12; 1973-04-20; cuid318 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 17)
    Original Format: 1/4"Open Reel Audio, Duration: 32 min., Preservation Note: "Full track, mono; 7.5 ips; uni-directional; stored tails out"
  - Sunrise Semester (Astro #37), 1973-04-12; 1973-04-23; cuid319 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 18)
  - Sunrise Semester Astro #38, 1973-04-12; 1973-04-25; cuid320 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 19)
  - Astro Episode #39, 1973-04-19; 1973-04-27; cuid321 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 20)
  - Sunrise Semester Astro #40, 1973-04-19; 1973-04-30; cuid322 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 21)
    Box reads, "7 1/2" Dr Engelbert L Schucking Transcribed 11/18/75"
  - Sunrise Semester Astro #41, 1973-04-19; 1973-05-02; cuid323 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 22)
    Box reads, "7 1/2" Dr. Engelbert Schucking Transcribed 12/2/75"
  - Astro 42 Sun Sem., 1973-04-26; 1973-05-04; cuid324 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255, Box Shared University Archives 118, Item 23)
    Original Format: 1/4" Open Reel Audio, Duration: 31 min., Preservation Note: "Full track, mono; 15 ips and 7.5 ips; uni-directional; 00:16:45;xx - 00:22:00;xx [end] - O-this is an excerpt from a different lecture by the same professor and for the same course. This portion may be a duplicate."
  - Sunrise Sem. Astro: #44, 1973-05-03; 1973-05-09; cuid325 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255)
  - Sunrise Sem Astro #45, 1973-05-03; 1973-05-11; cuid326 (Box 2, E-records nyuarchives_mc255)
- Series II. Accretions
  - Book: Einstein's Apple, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 1)